<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-24T10:44:07+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">21BCP140 Blog</title><subtitle>Learn how to build a three-tier application using Docker with our step-by-step tutorial series on our GitHub Pages blog. Follow along as we set up the database, backend, and frontend tiers, complete with Dockerfiles, Docker container creation, and integration of your roll number into the frontend. Explore each part with detailed explanations, code snippets, screenshots, and a GitHub repository for reference.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building a Three tier Application using docker explaination</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/2024/04/23/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Three tier Application using docker explaination" /><published>2024-04-23T08:06:31+05:30</published><updated>2024-04-23T08:06:31+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/2024/04/23/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/2024/04/23/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="docker-and-three-tier-architecture">Docker and Three-Tier Architecture</h1>

<h2 id="introduction-to-docker">Introduction to Docker</h2>

<p>Docker is a platform for developing, shipping, and running applications in containers. Containers allow developers to package an application with all of its dependencies into a standardized unit, ensuring that it will run consistently on any environment. Docker provides tools for building, deploying, and managing containers, making it easier to develop and deploy applications in various environments.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-three-tier-architecture">What is Three-Tier Architecture?</h2>

<p>Three-tier architecture is a software architecture pattern where an application is divided into three logical tiers or layers: the presentation tier, the application logic tier, and the data storage tier. Each tier has a specific role and responsibility:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Presentation Tier (Frontend):</strong> This tier is responsible for presenting information to the user and handling user interactions. It typically consists of user interfaces such as web browsers, mobile apps, or desktop applications.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Application Logic Tier (Backend):</strong> This tier contains the business logic of the application and is responsible for processing user requests, performing computations, and interacting with the data storage tier. It can include application servers, APIs, and microservices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Data Storage Tier (Database):</strong> This tier stores and manages the data used by the application. It can be a relational database, NoSQL database, file system, or any other data storage solution.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="using-docker-in-three-tier-architecture">Using Docker in Three-Tier Architecture</h2>

<p>Docker is particularly useful in implementing and deploying applications based on the three-tier architecture:</p>

<h3 id="1-database-tier">1. Database Tier</h3>

<p>In the database tier, Docker can be used to containerize the database management system (DBMS) such as PostgreSQL, MySQL, or MongoDB. Docker containers provide a lightweight and portable way to run databases, ensuring consistency across different environments.</p>

<h3 id="2-backend-tier">2. Backend Tier</h3>

<p>For the backend tier, Docker containers can encapsulate the application logic, including the web servers, APIs, and microservices. Developers can package their backend code and dependencies into Docker images, making it easy to deploy and scale the application components independently.</p>

<h3 id="3-frontend-tier">3. Frontend Tier</h3>

<p>In the frontend tier, Docker can be used to package and deploy the presentation layer components such as static web assets, JavaScript frameworks like React or Angular, and web servers like Nginx or Apache. Docker containers enable developers to build and deploy frontend applications with ease, ensuring consistency and reliability.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Docker simplifies the development, deployment, and management of applications based on the three-tier architecture. By using Docker containers for each tier, developers can achieve consistency, portability, and scalability in their applications, leading to faster development cycles and more efficient deployment processes.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Docker and Three-Tier Architecture]]></summary></entry></feed>